Finding Aid for Children’s Fund of Michigan records 1929-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Children's Fund of Michigan, records 1929-1965 1929-1961
Children's Fund of Michigan.
Detroit based philanthropic foundation created by Senator James J. Couzens and administered by William J. Norton to fund organizations in Michigan involved in child health and child guidance; includes administrative records, correspondence, reports of field visits, and topical files.
85963 BJ Bj2 UBJm
23 linear feet in 24 boxes
4 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group was the gift of William J. Norton (donor no. 4192 ) and came to the library in 1964 and 1965. A smaller addition was received in 1981.
The collection is open for research.
The Children's Fund of Michigan (CFM) was a charitable corporation created April 11, 1929 by Michigan Senator James Couzens with a gift of ten million dollars. The fund was to be used primarily for the benefit of the children of Michigan and was to be totally consumed within a period of twenty-five years. According to the terms of the trust, the fund was intended to "promote the health, welfare, happiness and development of the children of Michigan primarily, and elsewhere in the world." The fund was to be governed by a board of trustees. Officers of the organizations were to be chosen mainly from the trustees, but other individuals, not trustees, could be elected or appointed. The day-to-day administration of the fund rested in the capable hands of its executive vice-president and secretary, William J. Norton, himself a distinguished philanthropist.
In practice, the trustees divided the distribution of funds into three areas or divisions, each headed by a director. These were the Child Health Division administered by Bernard W. Carey (1929-1948) and Kenneth R. Gibson (1948-1954); the Child Guidance Division administered by Maud E. Watson (1930-1943) and John M. Dorsey (1944-1954); and the Research Division headed by Icie G. Macy-Hoobler (1930-1954). Special project grants were also awarded from time-to-time outside of these divisions.
The Child Health Division each year made the greatest expenditure of funds mainly in the area of dental care, rural health nursing services, and health education, and with the establishment of children's clinics at Marquette in the Upper Peninsula and Traverse City in the northern Lower Peninsula of Michigan. The division also made various yearly grants-in-aid to independent health agencies (such as the Visiting Nurse Association of Detroit) to help in financing their programs.
The Child Guidance Division was largely concerned with behavioral problems of "maladjusted children." Through different child guidance centers established in the state, the fund hoped to address the psychological problems afflicting children at risk because of the depression and because of other emotional and family-based difficulties. The largest of these centers was the Children's Center of Detroit. Eventually the work of these centers was taken over by the state department of mental health. Under the Child Guidance Division, the Edith Thomas Book Project was also funded, providing a circulating loan collection of sets of children's books to school districts and parent-teacher groups in communities of less than two thousand inhabitants.
The Division of Research, under the leadership of Dr. Icie Macy-Hoobler, conducted studies into problems pertaining to nutrition and maternal and infant growth. Initially undertaken in a laboratory operated by the fund, subsequent research was administered in a Child Research Center jointly created by the Children's Fund and the Children's Hospital of Michigan. Types of research funded included causes of the decay of children's teeth, research into orthodontic problems, problems relating to childhood tuberculosis, and causative factors leading to incidence of juvenile delinquency.
Although not a formal division, the Children's Fund distributed various grants-in-aid to groups concerned with providing recreational opportunities. These included the Boy Scouts and Girl Scouts of Detroit, the Young Men's Christian Association, the Green Pastures Camp of the Detroit Urban League, the Bay Cliff Health Camp in Marquette, Michigan, and Camp Stapleton operated by the Society of St. Vincent de Paul, among others.
Further details regarding the work of the Fund can be found in Biography of a Foundation written by William C. Richards and William J. Norton (1957). As specified in the trust instrument, the Children's Fund of Michigan ceased operation twenty-five years to the date of its creation having expended all of the organization's assets.
The records of the Children's Fund of Michigan (CFM) divide into six series: Administration, Alphabetical, Photographs, Scrapbooks, Financial, and Miscellaneous.
In the period beginning from the start of the depression and continuing through the mid-1950s, the Children's Fund of Michigan (CFM) was the state's most important private source of funding for programs having to do with children's health and recreational needs. Established just as the depression was beginning, it is impossible to overestimate the contribution made by this organization in such areas as rudimentary child health and dental care, pediatric care, in the establishment of area children's clinics, in its grants to nursing associations and hospitals, in its sponsorship of research in areas pertaining to childhood diseases and ailments, and in the funding and support of such youth-related organizations as the Girls and Boys Scouts, the Green Pastures Camp for Detroit area African American youth, and the Society of St. Vincent de Paul. The organization affected thousands of young lives at a time when help was most needed. The record of its contribution is fully documented through such records as minutes, correspondence, reports from the field, memoranda, and financial records. Topics documented within this collection include the condition of children and young people in mid-Twentieth Century America as the nation went through depression, world war, and the uncertainties of the post-war; the administration of a unique multi-million dollar charitable organization and how it allocated its resources; and, lastly, the activities during a twenty-five year period of the several statewide organizations begun or largely supported with CFM funding.
This record group consists of files from the CFM office in Detroit. The files are of CFM executive director and secretary, William J. Norton, and various other division directors, in particular Maud Watson and John M. Dorsey of the Child Guidance Division and Bernard W. Carey of the Child Health Division. They cover the period of 1929-1954, the twenty-five year life of the Fund, although there are included some papers dating up to the early 1960s. The presence of this later dated material is easily explained. As someone who was involved in social welfare organizations other than CFM, Norton continued to use the files (as he had in the past) for those papers relating to his other philanthropic and charitable organization activities. This filing practice, in addition to the fact that Norton (after 1954) continued to receive and file reports and memoranda from organizations and facilities that had received CFM funding, accounts for post-1954 materials in this record group. Norton was so closely identified with both CFM and the numerous local and state charitable organizations of the time that it is not feasible to divorce the two kinds of records - especially as Norton chose to file them as one. The researcher should note that the library has a separate William J. Norton collection that was received separately from the CFM records and which was most likely maintained in a different location. This Norton collection includes more personal materials not necessarily relating to the Children's Fund.
Subjects:
Charities--Michigan.; Child mental health--Michigan.; Child welfare--Michigan.; Children--Health and hygiene--Michigan.; Children's Hospital of Michigan.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Scrapbooks.; Dental clinics--Michigan.; Depressions--1929--United States.; Detroit (Mich.). Mayor's Interracial Committee.; Hospitals--Michigan--Detroit.; Hospitals--Michigan--Traverse City.; Hospitals--Michigan--Marquette.; Michigan. State Emergency Welfare Relief Commission.; Norton, William J. (William John), 1883-1975.; Philanthropists--Michigan.; Social service--Michigan--Societies, etc.; United Community Services of Metropolitan Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Alcona County (Mich.); Alger County (Mich.); Antrim County (Mich.); Arenac County (Mich.); Benzie County (Mich.); Charlevoix County (Mich.); Cheboygan County (Mich.); Children.; Children's Fund of Michigan.; Chippewa County (Mich.); Dwellings.; Ferries.; Gladwin County (Mich.); Grand Traverse County (Mich.); Houghton County (Mich.); Interiors.; Iosco County (Mich.); Iron County (Mich.); Isabella County (Mich.); Keweenaw County (Mich.); Lake County (Mich.); Mackinac County (Mich.); Menominee County (Mich.); Montmorency County (Mich.); Newaygo County (Mich.); Oceana County (Mich.); Ogemaw County (Mich.); Osceola County (Mich.); Oscoda County (Mich.); Parades and processions.; Public health--Michigan.; Roads--Michigan, Northern.; Roscommon County (Mich.); Schools--Michigan.; Sleds and sleighs.; Van Buren County (Mich.); Winter.
Contributors:
Carey, B. W.; Dorsey, John M. (John Morris), 1900-1978; Gibson, Kenneth Richard, 1895-1959.; Kenworthy, Marion E.; Watson, Maud E.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Administration 1929-1959
  The Administration (1929-1959; 5 linear feet) series includes documents pertaining to the establishment of the fund, annual reports, and minutes and resolutions of the board of trustees. Additionally this series includes reports from the field received by Norton from Child Health Division staff members. The three largest files in this series correspond to the three divisions within the CFM: the Research Laboratory, the Child Health Division, and the Child Guidance Division. Each of these files includes such documentation as annual reports, correspondence of division directors, and various other reports and memoranda. The Research Laboratory is the smallest of these, but the researcher should note that its director Icie Macy-Hoobler donated her professional files to the library separately, and included with them are her CFM papers.
  The Child Guidance Division subseries, in addition to annual reports and correspondence of one of its directors Maud Watson, is noteworthy for the correspondence exchanged between Norton and its other director John M. Dorsey. Dorsey was a distinguished psychiatrist and university educator who wrote long and thoughtful letters to Norton about child guidance and the kinds of programs needed to deal with the stresses confronting the state's young people, particularly urban youth.
  - Annual reports 1929-1953 (lacking 25th AR, 1954) (Box 1)
  - Partial summary of the activities of the CFM 1929-1942 (Box 1)
  - Trust instrument, articles of association, etc (Box 1)
  - By-laws 1930 (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees
    - Minutes 1929-1954 (Box 1)
    - Resolutions 1929-1933 (Box 1)
  - Executive Vice President and Secretary's File (William J. Norton)
    - Reports of field visits and other memoranda received mainly from the Child Health Division 1929-1938, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Reports of field visits and other memoranda received mainly from the Child Health Division 1941-1954, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Research Laboratory
    - Summary report of activities 1931-1939 (Box 2)
    - Notebook summarizing research programs sponsored by CFM, late 1930s (with reprints of principal articles) (Box 2)
    - Annual reports 1931/32-1951/52 (lacks 1932/33), 19 volumes booklets; 1 folders (Box 2)
    - Chronological files 1929-1954, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Child Health Division (see also "Executive Vice President and Secretary's file", box 1)
    - Annual reports 1929/30-1953/54, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - B.W. Carey reports, memos, etc. 1929-1936, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Field staff annual report analysis 1931/32 (Box 3)
    - Nursing Division
      - Annual report 1931/32 (Box 3)
      - Reports 1930, 1935-1939 of nursing service, 3 folders (Box 3)
        (also scattered throughout B.W. Carey files)
    - Central Michigan Children's Clinic, Traverse City (mainly correspondence and other materials received from clinic superintendents)
      - W.J. Norton files 1935-1957, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - Kenneth Gibson files 1952-1954 (Box 4)
    - Northern Michigan Children's Clinic, Marquette
      (mainly correspondence and other materials received from clinic superintendents)
      - W.J. Norton files 1930-1959, 8 folders (Box 4)
      - Robert MacRae files 1930-1933 (Box 4)
      - Kenneth Gibson files 1940-1954, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - St. Luke's Hospital
        - General 1930-1939 (Box 4)
        - Proposed new unit 1937-1939 (Box 4)
  - Child Guidance Division
    - Children's Center
      - Summary of eight years of child guidance under the Children's Fund of Michigan 1939 (Box 5)
      - Annual reports 1936/37-1952/53 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence of Maud Watson, director, with Dr. Marion E. Kenworthy 1931-1940 (Box 5)
      - Chronological files 1930-1955, 9 folders (Box 5)
      - John M. Dorsey files
        - Correspondence 1947-1951 with WJN (Box 5)
        - Various writings, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Alphabetical files 1929-1961
  The Alphabetical series (1929-1961; 8.7 linear feet) details CFM's relationship with organizations receiving grants or other types of support. Some of the larger sequences of files in this series concern the Michigan State Emergency Relief Administration, the Detroit and Pontiac Visiting Nurse Associations, CFM support of University of Michigan programs and research, and the Mayor's (Detroit) Interracial Commission. Included here is CFM's extensive correspondence file with Fund originator, James Couzens.
  - Alley, east side of building (Box 6)
  - American foundations (Box 6)
  - American Red Cross 1952-1955, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - An-Aq (Box 6)
  - Anderson, Lacy, Wilcox and Lawson (Box 6)
  - Ar (Box 6)
  - Arthritis and Rheumatism Foundation (Box 6)
  - Atlanta School of Social Work (Box 6)
  - Ball-Barg (Box 6)
  - Bark-Barr (Box 6)
  - Bath (Mich.) school disaster (Box 6)
  - Bat-Bd (Box 6)
  - Bay Cliff Health Camp (Box 6)
  - Bay Court (Box 6)
  - Berk-Berq (Box 6)
  - Berr-Bh (Box 6)
  - Bin-Bk (Box 6)
  - Bla-Blk (Box 6)
  - Boys Club of Detroit (Box 6)
  - Boys Club of Pontiac (Box 6)
  - Boy Scouts, Detroit Area Council (Box 6)
  - Boy Scouts-Various (Box 6)
  - Boy Scouts-Clinton Valley (Box 6)
  - Brain Disease Registry, Wayne University (Box 6)
  - Browning (Box 6)
  - Bru-Bt (Box 6)
  - Building needs of social agencies (correspondence and memoranda concerning) (Box 6)
  - Cam-Cao (Box 6)
  - Cap-Carq (Box 6)
  - Carr-Carz (Box 6)
  - Cass Community Church and Center (Box 6)
  - Cas-Cd (Box 6)
  - Che-Chn (Box 6)
  - Child Welfare League of America (Box 7)
  - Children's Hospital of Michigan, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Community Chest of Metropolitan Detroit 1948 (Box 7)
  - Cop-Cor (Box 7)
  - Council of Social Agencies 1941-1948 (Box 7)
  - Couzens, Frank (Box 7)
  - Couzens, James 1929-1936, 8 folders (Box 7)
  - Couzens (James) Memorial 1937 (Box 7)
  - Couzens, Mrs. James 1932-1960 (Box 7)
  - Cranbrook School (Box 7)
  - Cri-Ct (Box 7)
  - Day Care of Children Committee, Wayne County Council of Defense 1942-1943 (Box 7)
  - Dental caries (Bunting research) 1932, 1951 (Box 8)
  - Dental programs of the CFM: 25 year summary report 1954 (Box 8)
  - Detroit (general) 1935-1955 (Box 8)
  - Detroit Board of Education 1949-1958 (Box 8)
  - Detroit Department of Health 1938-1940 (Box 8)
  - Detroit Department of Recreation 1936-1939 (Box 8)
  - Detroit Mayor's Fact-Finding Committee re Detroit City Gas Company 1937, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Detroit Mayor's Inter-racial (sic) Commission (formerly Committee on Race Relations) 1941-1944, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Detroit Mayor's Unemployment Committee 1931-1933 (Box 8)
  - Detroit School Social Service Committee 1931-1940, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Detroit Section National Council of Jewish Women 1929-1939 (Box 8)
  - Detroit Thrift Gardens (Box 8)
  - Detroit Urban League (mainly re Green Pastures Camp), 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Federal Emergency Relief Administration 1933-1935 (Box 8)
  - Fi (Box 8)
  - Flint Mental Hygiene Association (Box 9)
  - Fos-Fq (Box 9)
  - Fra-Frd (Box 9)
  - Freund, Hugo 1929-1953, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Gea-Gen (Box 9)
  - Gibson, R. Lauren (paper 1930 entitled, "Summer Dental Program") (Box 9)
  - Girl Scouts (Detroit), 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Girl Scouts (Michigan) (Annual report of progress of Girl Scouting in Michigan 1944-1949 (Box 9)
  - Girl Scouts (national) 1940-1944, 1947-1953, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Gl-Goq (Box 9)
  - Grand Rapids Committee for Mental Hygiene (Box 9)
  - Greater Detroit Hospital Fund 1950-1951, 4 folders (Box 9)
  - Haa-Hars (Box 9)
  - Hamtramck-Proposed new health center 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - Handicapped children in Michigan (survey of their needs) 1929 (Box 9)
  - Health Council of Metropolitan Detroit 1942-1952 (Box 9)
  - Hi-Ht (Box 10)
  - Hunter, Howard (Box 10)
  - Ia-Iz (Box 10)
  - Ja-Jz (Box 10)
  - Jewish Community Center 1935-1948 (Box 10)
  - Joint Committee on Health Education 1936-1946 (Box 10)
  - Ka-Kz (Box 10)
  - La-Lz (Box 10)
  - Lewis, Samuel J. 1930-1938 (Box 10)
  - Loan Fund 1930-1931 (Box 10)
  - Maa-Mad (Box 10)
  - Madonna Guild 1932-1936 (Box 10)
  - Menninger Foundation 1945-1959 (Box 10)
  - Mer-Met (Box 10)
  - Michigan (general) 1950-1952, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Michigan Children's Aid Society 1932-1954, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Michigan Crippled Children Commission 1950-1958 (Box 10)
  - Michigan Department of Health 1929-1961 (Box 10)
  - Michigan Department of Mental Health 1948-1953 (Box 10)
  - Michigan Department of Public Instruction
    - 1931-1953 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Study of the Secondary School Curriculum 1941-1942, 3 folders
      - 1941-1942 (Box 10)
      - 1943-1945, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Michigan Infantile Paralysis Commission 1931-1940 (Box 11)
  - Michigan Society for Epileptic Children 1953-1954 (Box 11)
  - Michigan Society for Mental Health 1953-1959 (Box 11)
  - Michigan State Emergency Relief Administration 1933-1938, 6 folders (Box 11)
  - Michigan State Hospital Commission 1939-1943 (Box 11)
  - Michigan State Hospital Survey Committee 1944-1947, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Michigan State Medical Society 1940-1942 (Box 11)
  - Michigan Welfare League 1941-1953 (Box 11)
  - Michigan Welfare Relief and Study Commission 1936-1937 (Box 11)
  - Muskegon County Boarding Project 1937-1938 (Box 11)
  - Muskegon (various) (Box 11)
  - N (miscellaneous) (Box 12)
  - National (various organizations) 1945-1962, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - National Association for Mental Health (formerly National Committee for Mental Hygiene) 1938-1954 (Box 12)
  - National Conference of Social Work 1941-1962 (Box 12)
  - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis 1944-1954 (Box 12)
  - Nursing Field Work Association 1942 (Box 12)
  - O (miscellaneous) (Box 12)
  - Oakland County Probate Court 1940-1961, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Osborne Association 1945-1951 (Box 12)
  - Pa-Pg (miscellaneous) (Box 12)
  - Ph-Pz (miscellaneous) (Box 12)
  - Pentland School 1941-1950 (Box 12)
  - Peter Pan Nursery School 1948-1963 (Box 12)
  - Pontiac (miscellaneous) (Box 12)
  - Puerto Rico Child Health Committee 1930-1931 (Box 12)
  - R (miscellaneous) (Box 12)
  - Richards, William C (Box 12)
  - Sa-Sz (miscellaneous), 6 folders (Box 12)
  - St. Vincent de Paul, Society of 1929-1961, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Scholler, Peter 1932-1933 (Box 12)
  - Shady Trails Camp 1934-1948, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Stanley, Fred G. 1930-1934 (Box 12)
  - Student Aid Foundation 1948-1952 (Box 12)
  - Survey Associates 1933-1952 (Box 12)
  - Thomas (Edith Thomas Book Project) 1931-1954, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Traverse City State Hospital 1934-1938 (Box 13)
  - Union/United (miscellaneous) (Box 13)
  - Union Guardina Trust Company 1932-1938 (Box 13)
  - United China Relief 1941-1942 (Box 13)
  - United Community Services of Metropolitan Detroit (formed from merger of Community Chest and the Council of Social Agencies) 1951-1961, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - United Foundation 1949-1953 (Box 13)
  - United States Government (general) 1945-1954 (Box 13)
  - United States War Labor Board, Salary Stabilization Unit 1942-1945 (Box 13)
  - University of Michigan
    - General 1930-1954, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Dental caries research 1929-1934 (Box 13)
    - Epidemic diarrhoea of the newborn research 1941-1944 (Box 13)
    - Fresh Air Camp 1929-1948 (Box 13)
    - Gibson (Kenneth) file 1949-1953 (Box 13)
    - Institute of Health and Social Sciences 1936 (Box 13)
  - V (miscellaneous) (Box 14)
  - Visiting Nurse Association of Detroit 1936-1955, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Visiting Nurse Association of Pontiac 1936-1953 (Box 14)
  - W (miscellaneous) (Box 14)
  - War (miscellaneous) 1942-1946 (Box 14)
  - Wayne County (general) (Box 14)
  - Wayne County Training School 1942-1960 (Box 14)
  - Wayne University 1936-1960, 4 folders (Box 14)
  - Woman's Building Campaign 1927-1948, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Wright (Sophie Wright Settlement) 1936-1939 (includes photos) (Box 14)
  - X-Y (miscellaneous) (Box 14)
  - Youth Aliyah 1938-1945 (Box 14)
  - Young Men's Christian Association 1933-1959 (Box 14)
  - Young Women's Christian Association 1935-1954 (Box 14)
- Photographs 1930-circa 1965
  Photographs (1930-ca. 1965; .3 linear feet) is a small series of images relating to the Fund's work with the rural poor in northern Michigan and the Upper Peninsula, especially in the area of child health; also general photos of rural areas and rural children. Most of the photographs concern children as part of groups, either in schools, in health care clinics, or in recreational groups.
  - Boys Club of Detroit (Box 14)
  - Central Michigan Children's Clinic June 24, 1936 (Box 14)
  - Children-School groups (Box 14)
  - Children and families (Box 14)
  - Children with nurses and doctors (Box 14)
  - Children's Fund boards, committees, and personnel (Box 14)
  - Edith Thomas Book Project (bookmobile, children reading, book exhibit) (Box 14)
  - Health displays and parades (Box 14)
  - Homes (Box 14)
  - Northern Michigan Children's Clinic, Marquette, Michigan
    - Buildings (Box 14)
    - Patients 1930s (Box 14)
    - Patients 1940s-1950s (Box 14)
    - Patients with staff (Box 14)
    - Staff (Box 14)
  - Rural scenery (Box 14)
  - Rural transportation (Box 14)
  - Schools-exteriors (Box 14)
  - Schools-interiors (include health testing) (Box 14)
  - Winter scenes (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
- Scrapbooks 1929-1953
  The Scrapbook (1929-1953; 10 volumes in 3 boxes and 3 oversize volumes) series consist of volumes of clippings received from a clipping service and relating to the activities and grants made by CFM. The series covers the period from 1929 to 1954 with some gaps. The series is most complete for the 1930s when the CFM initiated many of its programs. Most of the articles are brief but coverage is from newspapers throughout the state. Occasionally, the volumes will contain a photograph or two.
  - April 1929-May 1932, 4 volumes (Box 15)
  - May 1932-February 1934, 2 volumes (Box 16)
  - February 1934-August 1936 (Volume 1)
  - September 1936-May 1937 (Box 17)
  - May 1937-1938 (selection) (Box 17)
  - July 1941-December 1948 (Volume 2)
  - 1949-1953 (Box 17)
  - Memorial scrapbook to James Couzens 1936 (Box 17)
  - History of Central Michigan Children's Clinic, Traverse City, Michigan 1936 (Volume 3)
- Financial 1929-1965